<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Doss-Gollin Lab @ Rice CEVE</title>
<link>https://dossgollin-lab.github.io/</link>
<atom:link href="https://dossgollin-lab.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.8.27</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>James Quoted in WSJ Article on Flood Risk Scores</title>
  <link>https://dossgollin-lab.github.io/posts/2026/2026-01-20-wsj-flood-risk.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>James was quoted in a <a href="https://www.wsj.com/real-estate/home-sales-zillow-first-street-disaster-score-bf91e565">Wall Street Journal article</a> by Jean Eaglesham and Nicole Friedman examining the accuracy and limitations of climate-disaster scores used by home listing platforms like Zillow and Redfin.</p>
<p>From the article:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>“Accurately estimating future flood risk at every property in a single city or watershed—let alone the entire United States—is fundamentally not possible given current knowledge,” said James Doss-Gollin, an assistant professor of engineering and a climate-risks specialist at Rice University in Houston.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>While flood risk models serve an important role in informing homebuyers and leveling the playing field between buyers, lenders, and insurers, we must be skeptical of claims that national, building-scale flood risk models are empirically “validated.” Probabilistic flood risk estimation involves not just flood modeling, but also estimates of the probability of extreme weather events based on imperfect models and short records—which cannot be validated in the traditional sense.</p>
<p>For more on this topic, see our recent <a href="https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.2409657122">PNAS paper</a> led by Adam Pollack on how uncertainty in flood risk estimates affects flood insurance policy.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>News</category>
  <guid>https://dossgollin-lab.github.io/posts/2026/2026-01-20-wsj-flood-risk.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>New PNAS Paper on the Need for Transparent Climate-Risk Research</title>
  <link>https://dossgollin-lab.github.io/posts/2026/2026-01-15-pnas-transparency.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>A new paper in <em>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</em>, led by Adam Pollack (now at the University of Iowa), argues that transparency is especially critical for climate-risk research—and that current practices fall short.</p>
<p>Most engineering products can be tested directly: a new material can be stress-tested regardless of whether its formula is secret. Climate risk estimates can’t. There’s no instrument that measures the probability of a 100-year flood, so when two models disagree—as they do for 76% of Los Angeles properties—we have no independent way to settle the question. Scrutiny of methods and assumptions is the only path to trust, yet only 4% of highly-cited climate-risk studies share both data and code.</p>
<p>The paper charts a course forward: climate-risk tools should be explainable, benchmarked, built on open foundations, and comparable across providers. Getting there will take more than good intentions from individual researchers—it requires institutional commitment to open science infrastructure.</p>
<p>See the <a href="../../bibliography/publications/article/pollack_transparency_2026.html">full paper</a> or the <a href="https://engineering.dartmouth.edu/news/researchers-call-for-more-transparency-in-climate-risk-science">Dartmouth press release</a>.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Publications</category>
  <guid>https://dossgollin-lab.github.io/posts/2026/2026-01-15-pnas-transparency.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Undergrad Position: Flood Extent Labeling</title>
  <link>https://dossgollin-lab.github.io/posts/2026/2026-01-14-flood-labeling-undergrad.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>We are recruiting undergraduate students to assist labeling flood extents using NOAA aerial imagery. This work involves manually identifying and delineating flooded areas using GIS software and will contribute directly to an active research project on flood mapping.</p>
<section id="what-you-will-do" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-you-will-do">What You Will Do</h2>
<ul>
<li>Manually identify and mask flood extent using GIS tools (QGIS)</li>
<li>Follow labeling guidelines to ensure data quality</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="time-commitment" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="time-commitment">Time Commitment</h2>
<ul>
<li>Approximately 8-10 hours per week, flexible schedule</li>
<li>Weekly progress check-in (less than 15 minutes)</li>
<li>Feedback session after finishing one region or target area</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="schedule-and-location" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="schedule-and-location">Schedule and Location</h2>
<ul>
<li>Mostly remote</li>
<li>In-person meetings for feedback sessions (Ryon 111)</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="skills-and-requirements" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="skills-and-requirements">Skills and Requirements</h2>
<ul>
<li>Basic familiarity with GIS software is helpful but not required</li>
<li>Reliable and able to meet weekly time commitments</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="what-youll-gain" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-youll-gain">What You’ll Gain</h2>
<ul>
<li>Hands-on experience with GIS and remote sensing data</li>
<li>Co-authorship on the resulting published dataset</li>
<li>A great opportunity to strengthen your resume or prepare for graduate school or research careers</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="compensation" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="compensation">Compensation</h2>
<p>This position is available for pay or for course credit, depending on your interest. If you are interested in credit, you will need to sign up soon.</p>
</section>
<section id="interested" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="interested">Interested?</h2>
<p>If you are interested in this opportunity, please reach out to <a href="../../people/pi/james-doss-gollin.html">James Doss-Gollin</a>, <a href="https://gori.blogs.rice.edu/team/">Avi Gori</a>, or <a href="../../people/grad-students/dongwook-kim.html">Dongwook Kim</a>.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>News</category>
  <guid>https://dossgollin-lab.github.io/posts/2026/2026-01-14-flood-labeling-undergrad.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Doss-Gollin Lab at AGU 2025</title>
  <link>https://dossgollin-lab.github.io/posts/2025/2025-12-30-agu.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>The Doss-Gollin Lab had an active presence at AGU 2025, held December 15-19 in New Orleans, Louisiana.</p>
<section id="lab-presentations" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="lab-presentations">Lab Presentations</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://dossgollin-lab.github.io/_assets/img/news/2025-12-15-agu-yuchen-poster.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:70.0%"></p>
<figcaption>Yuchen Lu presenting her poster at AGU 2025</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p><a href="../../people/grad-students/yuchen-lu.html">Yuchen Lu</a> presented a poster titled “A Hierarchical Bayesian Spatial Framework to Assess Nonstationary Rainfall Intensity, Frequency, and Duration in Texas” (NH13D-0410). The work proposes a hierarchical Bayesian spatial model that efficiently pools information across space and jointly models precipitation across multiple time durations, enabling nonstationary IDF curve analysis across Texas.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://dossgollin-lab.github.io/_assets/img/news/2025-12-15-agu-james-talk.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:70.0%"></p>
<figcaption>James Doss-Gollin giving his talk at AGU 2025</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p><a href="../../people/pi/james-doss-gollin.html">James Doss-Gollin</a> delivered a talk titled “TxRain: A Bayesian framework for integrating historical observations and model projections to develop nonstationary IDF curves” (H24A-07). This work addresses the challenge of developing nonstationary extreme rainfall models by integrating accurate but short weather station records with long-term climate model projections. James was also a coauthor on several other presentations at the conference.</p>
</section>
<section id="session-convening" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="session-convening">Session Convening</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://dossgollin-lab.github.io/_assets/img/news/2025-12-15-agu-james-chair.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:70.0%"></p>
<figcaption>James Doss-Gollin chairing a session at AGU 2025</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>James served as chair for two sessions at AGU 2025:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>NH31A: Advances in Urban Flood Risk Assessment and Adaptation I</strong> (co-chaired with Vivek Srikrishnan)</li>
<li><strong>NH43B: Interdisciplinary Advances in Catastrophe Modeling and Disaster Resilience: Bridging Science, Policy, and Practice II</strong> (co-chaired with Benjamin Felzer)</li>
</ul>
<p>Thanks to all our coauthors and session co-organizers for their collaboration, and we look forward to continuing these partnerships.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Events</category>
  <guid>https://dossgollin-lab.github.io/posts/2025/2025-12-30-agu.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>New Paper on Diffusion for Precipitation Downscaling Published in IEEE TGRS</title>
  <link>https://dossgollin-lab.github.io/posts/2025/2025-09-23-liu-generative.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>A new paper “Downscaling Extreme Precipitation with Wasserstein Regularized Diffusion,” published in IEEE Transactions on Geoscience and Remote Sensing <span class="citation" data-cites="liu_generative:2025">(Liu et al. 2025)</span>. This work is led by <a href="https://www.yuhaoliu.net/">Yuhao Liu</a>, a PhD student in Electrical and Computer Engineering, and is the culmination of extensive brainstorming and research collaboration with coauthors <a href="https://www.ece.rice.edu/~ashok/">Ashok Veeraraghavan</a>, <a href="https://www.ece.rice.edu/~guha/">Guha Balakrishnan</a>, and Qiushi Dai as well as <a href="../../people/pi/james-doss-gollin.html">James Doss-Gollin</a>.</p>
<p>Many assessments of rainfall and flood hazard require high-resolution precipitation data (e.g., 1-4 km). While coarse global datasets from reanalysis products exist, and fine-grained radar data is available for recent years, there is a critical gap in producing long-term, high-resolution historical datasets needed for robust climate and hydrological modeling. Existing deep learning methods for this <em>downscaling</em> or <em>super-resolution</em> task often fail to accurately capture the statistical properties of the most extreme, and therefore most dangerous, events.</p>
<p>We developed Wasserstein Regularized Diffusion (<code>WassDiff</code>), a novel generative AI framework. Unlike other diffusion models that can replicate the general distribution of rainfall, <code>WassDiff</code> is specifically designed to get the tails of the distribution right. It integrates a Wasserstein distribution-matching regularizer directly into the denoising process. This forces the model to pay close attention to the frequency and magnitude of extreme values, reducing the biases commonly seen in generative models for climate data.</p>
<p>Experiments show that <code>WassDiff</code> generates high-resolution precipitation fields that are more physically realistic and statistically accurate than those from competing models. It more faithfully reproduces the spatial patterns and, most importantly, the statistical characteristics of extreme rainfall, making it a more reliable tool for climate impact studies.</p>
<p>This work provides a significant step forward for both the machine learning and climate science communities. By creating more reliable high-resolution precipitation data, <code>WassDiff</code> can help scientists and engineers better assess flood risk, design more resilient infrastructure, and ultimately improve our understanding of how climate change impacts local communities.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
<span class="screen-reader-only">Note</span>Access
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>We are happy to share a copy upon request if you don’t have access to this journal.</p>
</div>
</div>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-liu_generative:2025" class="csl-entry">
Liu, Yuhao, James Doss-Gollin, Qiushi Dai, Ashok Veeraraghavan, and Guha Balakrishnan. 2025. <span>“Downscaling <span>Extreme Precipitation</span> with <span>Wasserstein Regularized Diffusion</span>.”</span> <em>IEEE Transactions on Geoscience and Remote Sensing</em>, 1–1. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1109/TGRS.2025.3611872">https://doi.org/10.1109/TGRS.2025.3611872</a>.
</div>
</div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Publications</category>
  <guid>https://dossgollin-lab.github.io/posts/2025/2025-09-23-liu-generative.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>CERCAT Funding for Tropical Cyclone Hazard Assessment Project</title>
  <link>https://dossgollin-lab.github.io/posts/2025/2025-09-02-cercat-tropical-cyclone.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>We’re thrilled to announce that our project, “A nonstationary joint probability method for tropical cyclone hazard assessment,” with <a href="https://gori.blogs.rice.edu/">Avantika Gori</a> as co-PI, has been selected for funding by the Consortium for Enhancing Resilience and Catastrophe Modeling (CERCAT) and officially kicks off today.</p>
<p>The Consortium for Enhancing Resilience and Catastrophe Modeling held its inaugural Industry Advisory Board Meeting on August 7-8, 2025, where our Industry Advisory Board played a critical role in providing project feedback and helping prioritize key projects for the consortium’s first year.</p>
<p>This collaborative project aims to develop innovative approaches for assessing tropical cyclone hazards under changing climate conditions, addressing the critical need for nonstationary methods that can account for evolving risk patterns.</p>
<p>We’re excited to be part of this collaborative effort alongside other groundbreaking projects focused on multi-hazard resilience, wildfire fragility curves, and AI-driven damage assessment.</p>
<p>For more information about CERCAT and the full portfolio of funded projects, visit <a href="https://www.catmodeling.org/news">the CERCAT website</a>.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>News</category>
  <guid>https://dossgollin-lab.github.io/posts/2025/2025-09-02-cercat-tropical-cyclone.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>New Paper on Bayesian Spatiotemporal Analysis of Extreme Rainfall in Environmental Research: Climate</title>
  <link>https://dossgollin-lab.github.io/posts/2025/2025-08-26-lu-spatiotemporal.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Congratulations to <a href="../../people/grad-students/yuchen-lu.html">Yuchen Lu</a> on her first first-author paper, “Bayesian spatiotemporal nonstationary model quantifies robust increases in daily extreme rainfall across the Western Gulf Coast,” which has been published open-access in Environmental Research: Climate <span class="citation" data-cites="lu_spatiotemporal:2025">(Lu, Seiyon Lee, and Doss-Gollin 2025)</span>!</p>
<p>This research represents the first step in Yuchen’s work, funded by Rice and the Texas Water Development Board, on incorporating robust estimates of nonstationarity into precipitation frequency estimates. She is currently working with colleagues at TAMU and TWDB to incorporate these insights and methods into Intensity-Duration-Frequency (IDF) curves for Texas, and we will be presenting updates at the upcoming AGU Fall meeting.</p>
<section id="summary" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p>We develop the Spatially Varying Covariates Model, a novel Bayesian hierarchical framework that integrates nonstationarity and regionalization to address the challenges of estimating extreme precipitation probabilities. Traditional models like NOAA Atlas 14 assume stationarity, potentially underestimating current and future risks due to climate change. Our model leverages spatial statistics, extreme value theory, and Bayesian inference to provide robust estimates that pool information across nearby locations while allowing for temporal trends.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://dossgollin-lab.github.io/_assets/img/pubs/lu_spatiotemporal_2025.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Out-of-sample validation results showing the model’s ability to predict at ungauged locations</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Applying this framework to daily rainfall data from the Western Gulf Coast, we identify robustly increasing trends in extreme precipitation intensity and variability throughout the study area, with notable spatial heterogeneity. The findings indicate a 10-35% increase in extreme rainfall over the past 80 years, with the largest changes around Houston and New Orleans. Through rigorous cross-validation, we demonstrate that our estimates are well-calibrated and reliable, even at ungauged locations.</p>
<p>Compared to NOAA Atlas 14, our model suggests that current guidelines may underestimate future risks in many locations, highlighting the need for updated engineering designs that account for climate change impacts. Future projections for 2050 indicate that return levels will exceed current guidelines at most locations across the region.</p>
<p>Shout out also to coauthor Ben Seiyon Lee for patiently sharing his insights and expertise, and to colleagues at Rice, AGU, STAHY 2023, and ER: Climate for helpful suggestions and discussion.</p>
<p>For more details, see <a href="../../bibliography/publications/article/lu_spatiotemporal_2025.html">here</a>.</p>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-lu_spatiotemporal:2025" class="csl-entry">
Lu, Yuchen, Benjamin Seiyon Lee, and James Doss-Gollin. 2025. <span>“Bayesian Spatiotemporal Nonstationary Model Quantifies Robust Increases in Daily Extreme Rainfall Across the <span>Western Gulf Coast</span>.”</span> <em>Environmental Research: Climate</em> 4 (3): 035016. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1088/2752-5295/adf56e">https://doi.org/10.1088/2752-5295/adf56e</a>.
</div>
</div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Publications</category>
  <guid>https://dossgollin-lab.github.io/posts/2025/2025-08-26-lu-spatiotemporal.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Updated Thoughts on the Guadalupe Flood</title>
  <link>https://dossgollin-lab.github.io/posts/2025/2025-07-08-guadalupe-flood.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>I’ve had a chance to read, listen, and speak with journalists and colleagues over the past day. Here are a few points that I think are important to communicate to journalists and the public, and that I wish I’d been able to communicate more clearly.</p>
<p>This was, first and foremost, a <strong>horrific tragedy</strong>. The pain of families who can’t locate their loved ones is unfathomable. The current focus is correctly on finding anyone who may still be alive, on supporting grieving families and communities, and on providing aid to those who have lost everything. However, this event <strong>also highlights systemic failures</strong> that must be addressed to prevent future tragedies.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p><strong>Building in the floodway is dangerous.</strong> The floodway is the area where water flows fastest and deepest during a flood. It <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/ucifloodlab_its-absolutely-tragic-that-so-many-young-activity-7347421268201132033-4fTV?utm_source=share&amp;utm_medium=member_desktop&amp;rcm=ACoAAAr66-cBAxyypBAXNFrv8xul5KsrgSYTorA">appears</a> that Camp Mystic was built in the floodway of the Guadalupe River, which is a profoundly dangerous place to build a camp for children. In most communities, likely including Kerr County (I have not verified local regulations beyond scattered reporting), new construction or major renovations would trigger some scrutiny of flood risk, but building codes are not often applied retroactively to existing structures. While it is <em>socially and financially costly</em> to abandon or existing structures, <strong>safety must come first</strong>.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Need for flood alert and response systems.</strong> The SSPEED Center, of which I am a member, has built real-time flood forecasts for Houston, and we (along with other groups) have the capability to build a similar system for the Guadalupe River, given time, resources, and collaborators. As my colleague Phil Bedient has eloquently <a href="https://www.houstonchronicle.com/opinion/outlook/article/texas-flash-flood-prevent-gauge-warnings-20759811.php">argued</a>, we need to build a real-time flood forecasting system for the Guadalupe River.</p>
<ul>
<li>A critical component of this is enhancing <strong>real-time data collection</strong>, namely stream and rainfall gauges, to monitor floods in real time. The Upper Guadalupe River has five stream gauges along its roughly 230 mile length, and some of the gauges were not functioning during the flood. Better data collection is essential to understanding and responding to floods.</li>
<li><strong>The weather forecasts and warnings were generally good.</strong> The National Weather Service issued appropriate warnings as sources below describe in detail. However, predicting the <strong>exact magnitude and location</strong> of extreme rainfall is inherently uncertain, especially in complex terrain like the Texas Hill Country. The National Weather Service correctly identified the risk of heavy rainfall and flash flooding, and issued appropriate and timely warnings, with certainty and accuracy increasing as the event approached.</li>
<li>Alerts without <strong>trust and plans</strong> do not save lives. People need to get the alerts, understand what they mean, and know what steps to take. Building a flood prediction model is a necessary, but not sufficient, step to saving</li>
<li>There is a trade-off between <strong>certainty and lead time</strong>. Individuals and communities can take actions to prepare for flash floods, but these actions require time to implement. Unfortunately, the hydrology of the Guadalupe River means that the time from rain to flood can be very short. This means that if you wait until the rain has already fallen, or worse until the rivers are already rising, you can only take a very limited set of actions. On the other hand, if you take action based on forecasts, you have more time to prepare, but the forecasts are inherently uncertain and you will sometimes take action that turns out to be unnecessary.</li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
<p>I am not an expert on disaster response, communication, or the many agencies involved in flood response in this region, so I am in no position to point fingers or assign blame. However, it is unacceptable that an advanced society can place so little value on human life that we allow events like this to occur. There must be <strong>constructive accountability</strong> to ensure that we avoid preventable tragedies like this in the future.</p>
<section id="further-reading" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="further-reading">Further reading</h2>
<p>There has been a lot of excellent reporting on this horrific event. Here are some sources that I’ve found especially useful:</p>
<section id="general-coverage" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="general-coverage">General Coverage</h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2025/07/07/us/texas-flooding-map-guadalupe-river.html">NY Times Coverage</a> has generally been quite good</li>
<li>Houston Chronicle: <a href="https://www.houstonchronicle.com/projects/2025/texas-camp-mystic-guadalupe-fema-floodplains/"><em>Camp Mystic and others hit by deadly floods were built partly in ‘extremely hazardous’ flood zones</em></a></li>
<li>Read (or, like me, listen to) Samantha Montano’s book <a href="https://libro.fm/audiobooks/9781488211720-disasterology"><em>Disasterology</em></a></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="meteorology-and-weather-alerts" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="meteorology-and-weather-alerts">Meteorology and Weather Alerts</h3>
<ul>
<li>The Eyewall: <a href="https://theeyewall.com/making-sense-of-the-weather-that-led-to-a-horrible-texas-flooding-tragedy-plus-tropical-storm-chantal/"><em>Making sense of the weather that led to a horrible Texas flooding tragedy, plus Tropical Storm Chantal</em></a></li>
<li>Andrew Dessler does a good job of <a href="https://www.theclimatebrink.com/p/update-on-texas-flooding">explaining</a> the role of climate change in this event</li>
<li>Marshall Shepherd <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/marshallshepherd/2025/07/05/catastrophic-flooding-in-texaswere-there-warnings/"><em>Catastrophic flooding in Texas: Were there warnings?</em></a> provides a deep dive into the meteorological communication</li>
<li>Daniel Swain’s <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/weatherwest.bsky.social/post/3lta4d3vfk22z">Bluesky Thread</a> also gets into the role of early warnings, communication, and dissemination</li>
<li>Texas Tribune’s <a href="https://www.texastribune.org/2025/07/08/texas-weather-service-warning-kerr-county/"><em>Weather warnings gave officials a 3 hour, 21 minute window to save lives in Kerr County. What happened then remains unclear.</em></a></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="recommendations" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="recommendations">Recommendations</h3>
<ul>
<li>My colleague (and SSPEED Center director) Phil Bedient’s opinion piece in the Houston Chronicle <a href="https://www.houstonchronicle.com/opinion/outlook/article/texas-flash-flood-prevent-gauge-warnings-20759811.php"><em>Flash-flooding deaths can be prevented, says storm expert. Here’s what Texas needs to do.</em></a></li>
<li><a href="https://thehill.com/opinion/congress-blog/3702450-hurricane-ian-is-proof-the-us-needs-a-national-disaster-safety-board/"><em>Hurricane Ian is proof: The US needs a national disaster safety board</em></a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.ready.gov/floods">FEMA</a>, the <a href="https://www.redcross.org/get-help/how-to-prepare-for-emergencies/types-of-emergencies/flood.html">Red Cross</a>, and the <a href="https://www.weather.gov/safety/flood">National Weather Service</a> all have excellent resources on flood preparedness and response that you should <strong>print out and put on your fridge</strong> if you live in an area prone to flooding.</li>
</ul>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>News</category>
  <category>Floods</category>
  <category>Texas</category>
  <guid>https://dossgollin-lab.github.io/posts/2025/2025-07-08-guadalupe-flood.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Call for Abstracts: AGU Fall Meeting 2025 Sessions</title>
  <link>https://dossgollin-lab.github.io/posts/2025/2025-06-18-agu2025-sessions.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>The abstract submission deadline for AGU Fall Meeting 2025 is approaching! <a href="../../people/pi/james-doss-gollin.html">James</a> is co-convening three exciting sessions that span the interdisciplinary challenges at the intersection of natural hazards, human systems, and decision-making under uncertainty. We encourage submissions from researchers across disciplines who are working on these critical challenges.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-important callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
<span class="screen-reader-only">Important</span>Submit Your Abstract!
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Don’t miss the opportunity to share your research and connect with leading experts in these areas. Visit the <a href="https://www.agu.org/fall-meeting">AGU Fall Meeting website</a> for submission guidelines and deadlines.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>These sessions represent exciting opportunities to engage with cutting-edge research that bridges disciplines and advances our understanding of complex environmental challenges. Questions about any of these sessions? Feel free to <a href="../../contact.html">reach out</a>!</p>
<section id="session-1-multisector-dynamics-and-uncertainty" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="session-1-multisector-dynamics-and-uncertainty">Session 1: MultiSector Dynamics and Uncertainty</h2>
<p><strong><a href="https://agu.confex.com/agu/agu25/prelim.cgi/Session/250235">GC081 - MultiSector Dynamics: Uncertainty Characterization for Coupled Natural-Human Systems</a></strong></p>
<p>Multi-sector and coupled natural-human systems often feature complex adaptive dynamics, including feedbacks and tipping points, and involve many uncertainties. However, models of coupled natural-human systems often fail to characterize uncertainty and its propagation across systems. This session invites contributions addressing the challenge of uncertainty characterization for systems that bridge sectors (e.g., energy, water, transportation) and scales to understand their dynamics and improve decision-making.</p>
<p><strong>Conveners:</strong> Abigail Nora Birnbaum (PNNL), James Doss-Gollin (Rice), Jonathan Lamontagne (Tufts), Vivek Srikrishnan (Cornell)</p>
</section>
<section id="session-2-urban-flood-risk-assessment" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="session-2-urban-flood-risk-assessment">Session 2: Urban Flood Risk Assessment</h2>
<p><strong><a href="https://agu.confex.com/agu/agu25/prelim.cgi/Session/251344">NH001 - Advances in Urban Flood Risk Assessment and Adaptation</a></strong></p>
<p>Flooding is the natural hazard with the greatest economic and social impacts in the United States. This session invites contributions aimed at improving the understanding and quantification of urban flood risks, including multi-scale hazards, exposure and vulnerability dynamics, model validation, stakeholder engagement insights, and adaptation strategies that leverage generalizable insights across watersheds.</p>
<p><strong>Conveners:</strong> James Doss-Gollin (Rice), Adam Pollack (Dartmouth), Vivek Srikrishnan (Cornell), Abby Sullivan (Philadelphia Office of Sustainability), Marissa Webber (UNC Chapel Hill)</p>
</section>
<section id="session-3-catastrophe-modeling-and-disaster-resilience" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="session-3-catastrophe-modeling-and-disaster-resilience">Session 3: Catastrophe Modeling and Disaster Resilience</h2>
<p><strong><a href="https://agu.confex.com/agu/agu25/prelim.cgi/Session/249693">NH026 - Interdisciplinary Advances in Catastrophe Modeling and Disaster Resilience: Bridging Science, Policy, and Practice</a></strong></p>
<p>Climate change and growing exposure drive increases in the frequency and impact of natural hazards, emphasizing the need for accurate, ethical, and actionable catastrophe models. This session seeks interdisciplinary approaches that integrate geophysical, hydrological, and socio-technical systems, with particular encouragement for submissions exploring ethical, equity, and policy-relevant dimensions of catastrophe modeling.</p>
<p><strong>Conveners:</strong> Benjamin S Felzer (Lehigh), James Doss-Gollin (Rice), Avantika Gori (Rice), Yi-Chen Ethan Yang (UMASS)</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Events</category>
  <category>AGU</category>
  <guid>https://dossgollin-lab.github.io/posts/2025/2025-06-18-agu2025-sessions.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>James on Telemundo Special Bajo la Amenaza del Golfo</title>
  <link>https://dossgollin-lab.github.io/posts/2025/2025-06-01-telemundo.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>James Doss-Gollin was interviewed by <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/pablosancheztv/">Pablo Sánchez Núñez</a> of Telemundo Houston for a special report titled “Bajo la Amenaza del Golfo” (Under the Threat of the Gulf). The program explored the risks of hurricanes and other extreme weather events facing Houston, and the region’s ongoing efforts to build resilience. A brief segment from James’s interview was featured. This was a wonderful opportunity to connect with Spanish-speaking members of the community!</p>
<p>You can watch the segment <a href="https://www.telemundohouston.com/noticias/bajo-la-amenaza-del-golfo-parte-1-2/2494095/">here</a>.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://dossgollin-lab.github.io/_assets/img/news/2025-06-01-telemundo.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>James and Pablo</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>News</category>
  <guid>https://dossgollin-lab.github.io/posts/2025/2025-06-01-telemundo.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Congratulations to Yuchen Lu for Passing Her Thesis Proposal!</title>
  <link>https://dossgollin-lab.github.io/posts/2025/2025-04-30-yuchen-proposal.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>We are thrilled to announce that <a href="../../people/grad-students/yuchen-lu.html">Yuchen Lu</a> has successfully passed her thesis proposal defense titled “Probabilistic Analysis of Nonstationary Hydroclimate Extremes!” ]This marks a significant milestone as Yuchen becomes the first PhD candidate in our research group.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://dossgollin-lab.github.io/_assets/img/news/2025-04-30-yuchen-proposal.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Yuchen and her committee members</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Yuchen presented her research with confidence and expertise, demonstrating a deep understanding of nonstationary hydroclimate extremes and her innovative approaches to probabilistic analysis. Her work promises to make significant contributions to our understanding of changing extreme weather patterns and their implications for infrastructure design and risk management. Her first paper is already under review <span class="citation" data-cites="lu_spatiotemporal:2025">(Lu, Seiyon Lee, and Doss-Gollin 2025)</span>, and future work is forthcoming.</p>
<p>We would like to express our sincere gratitude to her committee members, Dr.&nbsp;Phil Bedient, Dr.&nbsp;Katherine Ensor, and Dr.&nbsp;Avantika Gori, for their thoughtful feedback and guidance throughout this process.</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-lu_spatiotemporal:2025" class="csl-entry">
Lu, Yuchen, Benjamin Seiyon Lee, and James Doss-Gollin. 2025. <span>“Bayesian Spatiotemporal Nonstationary Model Quantifies Robust Increases in Daily Extreme Rainfall Across the <span>Western Gulf Coast</span>.”</span> <em>Environmental Research: Climate</em> 4 (3): 035016. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1088/2752-5295/adf56e">https://doi.org/10.1088/2752-5295/adf56e</a>.
</div>
</div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Congratulations</category>
  <guid>https://dossgollin-lab.github.io/posts/2025/2025-04-30-yuchen-proposal.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Join Us at the Texas Climate Conference 2025</title>
  <link>https://dossgollin-lab.github.io/posts/2025/2025-04-02-texas-climate-conference.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://si.rice.edu/sites/g/files/bxs5416/files/inline-images/TX%20Climate%20Conference-Header.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:80.0%"></p>
<figcaption>Texas Climate Conference</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>We are excited to invite you to the <strong>Texas Climate Conference 2025</strong>, a 1.5-day event at Rice University on April 10-11, 2025. This conference will bring together scientists, policymakers, and community stakeholders to discuss science and solutions on four critical Texas climate themes:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Extreme Heat</strong></li>
<li><strong>Flooding and Water Resources</strong></li>
<li><strong>Sea Level Rise and Coastal Hazards</strong></li>
<li><strong>Human Health</strong></li>
</ul>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
<span class="screen-reader-only">Tip</span>More info
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>For more details and registration, visit the <a href="https://si.rice.edu/texas-climate-conference-2025">conference website</a>.</p>
</div>
</div>
<section id="event-highlights" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="event-highlights">Event Highlights</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Keynote Address</strong> by Katharine Hayhoe (The Nature Conservancy): “Climate Change in the Gulf Coast: Challenges, Opportunities, Solutions”</li>
<li><strong>Thematic Keynotes</strong> on extreme heat, flooding, sea level rise, and health challenges</li>
<li><strong>Networking Opportunities</strong> for students and early-career researchers</li>
<li><strong>Working Group Sessions</strong> to develop actionable strategies for climate resilience</li>
</ul>
<p>We hope to see you there!</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Events</category>
  <guid>https://dossgollin-lab.github.io/posts/2025/2025-04-02-texas-climate-conference.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Successful Nature-Based Solutions Workshop at Rice University</title>
  <link>https://dossgollin-lab.github.io/posts/2025/2025-03-03-nbs-workshop.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>We are thrilled to share the success of the <strong>Nature-Based Solutions for a Resilient Gulf Coast Workshop</strong>, held on March 3-4, 2025, at Rice University. This two-day event, funded by the Rice Sustainability Institute, Rice Creative Ventures, and Rice Water Institute, with administrative support from the Rice SSPEED Center, brought together experts from academia, government, non-profits, and industry to discuss innovative strategies for enhancing resilience through nature-based solutions (NBS) in the Gulf Coast region.</p>
<div class="center">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://dossgollin-lab.github.io/_assets/img/research/2025-03-03-nbs-workshop.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:60.0%"></p>
<figcaption>Dr.&nbsp;Phil Bedient (Rice), True Furrh (Rice), Dr.&nbsp;Nick Fang (UT Arlington), Dr.&nbsp;Noemi Vergopolan (Rice), Dr.&nbsp;James Doss-Gollin (Rice), Jerry Cotter, and Dr.&nbsp;Fouad Jaber (TAMU AgriLife) following the Inland Flood &amp; Hydrologic Modeling/ Rainfall &amp; Climate Impacts panel</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<section id="workshop-highlights" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="workshop-highlights">Workshop Highlights</h2>
<p>The workshop featured:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Technical presentations</strong> on quantifying NBS benefits, design strategies, and co-production with communities.</li>
<li><strong>Interactive breakout sessions</strong> where participants worked collaboratively to identify challenges and opportunities for NBS implementation.</li>
<li><strong>Panel discussions</strong> with representatives from academia, government, and industry, focusing on fostering partnerships and scaling solutions.</li>
<li><strong>Networking opportunities</strong> to build connections and strengthen collaborations among attendees.</li>
</ul>
<p>Participants shared insights, discussed ongoing research, and explored actionable strategies to advance NBS implementation across the Gulf Coast.</p>
</section>
<section id="thank-you" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="thank-you">Thank You!</h2>
<p>A heartfelt thank you to the attendees, sponsors, organizers, and staff. We look forward to continuing these important conversations and building on the connections established during the workshop.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Events</category>
  <guid>https://dossgollin-lab.github.io/posts/2025/2025-03-03-nbs-workshop.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 03 Mar 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Bayesian Model Reveals Rising Extreme Rainfall on Gulf Coast</title>
  <link>https://dossgollin-lab.github.io/posts/2025/2025-02-05-preprint-bayesian-precip.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Our preprint, led by <a href="../../people/grad-students/yuchen-lu.html">Yuchen Lu</a> and titled “Bayesian Spatiotemporal Nonstationary Model Quantifies Robust Increases in Daily Extreme Rainfall Across the Western Gulf Coast”, is now live on ArXiV <span class="citation" data-cites="lu_spatiotemporal:2025">(Lu, Seiyon Lee, and Doss-Gollin 2025)</span>.</p>
<section id="summary" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p>We develop a novel Bayesian hierarchical model, the Spatially Varying Covariates Model, to address the challenges of estimating nonstationary extreme precipitation probabilities. Traditional models often assume stationarity, potentially underestimating risks due to climate change. Our model integrates nonstationarity and regionalization, leveraging spatial statistics and extreme value theory to provide robust estimates of extreme precipitation events. We validate our approach using daily rainfall data from the Western Gulf Coast, revealing significant increases in extreme precipitation intensity and variability, particularly around Houston and New Orleans.</p>
<p>Our model demonstrates superior performance compared to traditional stationary models and nonstationary models that do not incorporate spatial pooling. Through rigorous cross-validation, we show that our estimates are well-calibrated and reliable, even at ungauged locations. The findings indicate a 10-35% increase in extreme rainfall over the past 80 years, with the largest changes in coastal areas. Compared to NOAA Atlas 14, our model suggests that current guidelines may underestimate future risks, highlighting the need for updated engineering designs to account for climate change impacts. This framework offers a practical and theoretically sound method for estimating nonstationary extreme precipitation probabilities, applicable to various regions and climate variables.</p>
</section>
<section id="read-more" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="read-more">Read More</h2>
<p>Our paper is currently undergoing peer review, so results should be treated as preliminary. For more details, see <a href="../../bibliography/publications/article/lu_spatiotemporal_2025.html">here</a>.</p>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-lu_spatiotemporal:2025" class="csl-entry">
Lu, Yuchen, Benjamin Seiyon Lee, and James Doss-Gollin. 2025. <span>“Bayesian Spatiotemporal Nonstationary Model Quantifies Robust Increases in Daily Extreme Rainfall Across the <span>Western Gulf Coast</span>.”</span> <em>Environmental Research: Climate</em> 4 (3): 035016. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1088/2752-5295/adf56e">https://doi.org/10.1088/2752-5295/adf56e</a>.
</div>
</div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Publications</category>
  <guid>https://dossgollin-lab.github.io/posts/2025/2025-02-05-preprint-bayesian-precip.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>NSF Grant to Study Flood Resilience in Rural Texas</title>
  <link>https://dossgollin-lab.github.io/posts/2025/2025-01-24-nsf-rural-flood.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>We’re excited to announce that Rice University, in collaboration with The University of Texas at Austin and Texas A&amp;M University’s Institute for Disaster Resilient Texas (IDRT), has been awarded a $1 million grant from the National Science Foundation’s Confronting Hazards, Impacts and Risks for a Resilient Planet Program (CHIRRP). <a href="../../people/pi/james-doss-gollin.html">James Doss-Gollin</a> and <a href="https://gori.blogs.rice.edu/team/">Avantika Gori</a> (Rice) will join Keri Stephens (UT Austin), and Andrew Juan (TAMU) on a project to develop transformative approaches for improving flood resilience in rural Texas communities.</p>
<p>The project aims to create a performance-based framework that bridges critical gaps in flood hazard assessment and mitigation strategies for rural communities. Working in the rural communities of <a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/au1qoQeuwNLF7Pp68">Fort Hancock</a> and <a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/XxeSF3fvVr41vHXE7">Premont</a>, Texas, we will develop new methods to characterize flood risks and co-design mitigation strategies that reflect local priorities. We’re particularly focused on identifying adaptations that address both frequent and extreme flood events, and that are scalable to communities with similar characteristics.</p>
<p>For more details, see the <a href="https://idrt.tamug.edu/idrt-team-builds-upon-drip-work-for-new-nsf-grant/">press release from IDRT</a> or <a href="https://www.nsf.gov/awardsearch/showAward?AWD_ID=2440167">the NSF award</a>).</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>News</category>
  <guid>https://dossgollin-lab.github.io/posts/2025/2025-01-24-nsf-rural-flood.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Doss-Gollin Lab at AGU 2024</title>
  <link>https://dossgollin-lab.github.io/posts/2024/2024-12-05-agu.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>We look forward to seeing you at AGU 2024! Our friends at the <a href="https://ai4climaterrr.rice.edu/">AI4ClimateRRR cluster</a> will be at the conference as well – for a list of presentations, see <a href="https://ai4climaterrr.rice.edu/posts/2024-12-05-agu.html">here</a></p>
<section id="tuesday" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tuesday">Tuesday</h3>
<ul>
<li>Poster: <a href="https://agu.confex.com/agu/agu24/meetingapp.cgi/Paper/1709468">GC23D-0279Graph Residual Transformer + Gated Recurrent Unit (GRU) for Global Numerical Weather Prediction</a></li>
<li>Poster: <a href="https://agu.confex.com/agu/agu24/meetingapp.cgi/Paper/1621742">PP21C-0473Changes in Texas Rainfall Characteristics During the Last Deglaciation in Speleothem Proxies and Water Isotope-enabled Model Simulations</a></li>
<li>Talk: <a href="https://agu.confex.com/agu/agu24/meetingapp.cgi/Paper/1711820">GC24H-01Assessing and Managing Climate Risks to Electricity Systems in an Era of Climate Change and Energy Transition</a></li>
<li>Talk: <a href="https://agu.confex.com/agu/agu24/meetingapp.cgi/Paper/1624973">NH23G-06TxRAIN-Observational: A Hierarchical Bayesian Spatial Framework to Assess Nonstationary Rainfall Intensity, Frequency, and Duration in Texas</a></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="thursday" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="thursday">Thursday</h3>
<ul>
<li>Poster Session: <a href="https://agu.confex.com/agu/agu24/meetingapp.cgi/Session/224843">NH41C - Hybrid Modeling and Digital Twin Systems for Flood Hazard Prediction and Risk Assessment at Different Spatial Scales</a></li>
<li>Poster: <a href="https://agu.confex.com/agu/agu24/meetingapp.cgi/Paper/1638085">NH41C-2328Pluvial Flood Emulation with Hydraulics-informed Message Passing</a></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="friday" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="friday">Friday</h3>
<ul>
<li>Talk: <a href="https://agu.confex.com/agu/agu24/meetingapp.cgi/Paper/1711605">NH51A-01Advancing Urban Flood Hazard Characterization through Machine Learning: Challenges and Opportunities</a></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://dossgollin-lab.github.io/posts/2024/2024-12-05-agu.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Announcing AI for Climate Risk and Resilience at Rice</title>
  <link>https://dossgollin-lab.github.io/posts/2024/2024-08-23-ai4climaterrr.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>We’re delighted to announce the launch of a new project, <em>AI for Climate Risk and Resilience at Rice</em> (AI4ClimateRRR), which will bring together researchers from across the university to develop new tools for understanding and addressing climate risks. AI4ClimateRRR is a cluster within the Ken Kennedy Institute. Monthly meetings are available to the Rice community.</p>
<p>For more, see <a href="https://ai4climaterrr.rice.edu/">the project website</a>.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>News</category>
  <guid>https://dossgollin-lab.github.io/posts/2024/2024-08-23-ai4climaterrr.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 23 Aug 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Welcome Dongwook!</title>
  <link>https://dossgollin-lab.github.io/posts/2024/2024-08-22-welcome-dongwook.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>We’re delighted to welcome <a href="../../people/grad-students/dongwook-kim.html">Dongwook Kim</a> to the lab! Dongwook joins us Burin Co., Ltd.&nbsp;in Seoul, where he was working as a research engineer. Prior that that, he earned a BS and MS at Hanyang University. Dongwook’s interests include water resources, flood risk, tropical cyclones, and infrastructure risk assessment.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Welcome</category>
  <guid>https://dossgollin-lab.github.io/posts/2024/2024-08-22-welcome-dongwook.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 22 Aug 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Pluvial Flood Emulation with Hydraulics-informed Message Passing accepted to ICML 2024</title>
  <link>https://dossgollin-lab.github.io/posts/2024/2024-06-09-kazadi-icml.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Our paper titled “Pluvial Flood Emulation with Hydraulics-informed Message Passing” has been accepted to the 2024 International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML) <span class="citation" data-cites="kazadi_icml:2024">(Kazadi, Doss-Gollin, and Silva 2024)</span>.</p>
<p>Given a geographical region and precipitation data, our model predicts water depths in an auto-regressive fashion using a message-passing framework inspired by the conservation of momentum and mass as expressed in the shallow-water equations. This allows the model to effectively capture the propagation of water flow, particularly during the early stages of flooding when the water is scarce.</p>
<p>Our empirical results, based on a dataset covering 9 regions and 7 historical precipitation events, demonstrate that our model outperforms existing baselines, providing accurate simulations even in complex topographies. This solution achieves accurate results using real ground elevation data. Additionally, our model excels in predicting flood dynamics for unseen storms and watersheds, showcasing its robustness and generalization capabilities.</p>
<p>For more details, see <a href="../../bibliography/publications/conference/kazadi_icml_2024.html">here</a>. This is an exciting space, and we are looking forward to sharing more updates on our ongoing research in this critical area!</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-kazadi_icml:2024" class="csl-entry">
Kazadi, Arnold, James Doss-Gollin, and Arlei Silva. 2024. <span>“Pluvial Flood Emulation with Hydraulics-Informed Message Passing.”</span> In <em>Forty-<span>First International Conference</span> on <span>Machine Learning</span></em>. <a href="https://openreview.net/forum?id=kIHIA6Lr0B">https://openreview.net/forum?id=kIHIA6Lr0B</a>.
</div>
</div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Publications</category>
  <guid>https://dossgollin-lab.github.io/posts/2024/2024-06-09-kazadi-icml.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 09 Jun 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>How extreme was the recent San Jacinto River rainfall?</title>
  <link>https://dossgollin-lab.github.io/posts/2024/2024-05-14-san-jac-idf.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Earlier this month, persistent and intense rainfall to the northeast of Houston caused severe flooding on the San Jacinto River, <a href="https://www.pbs.org/newshour/nation/southeastern-texas-sees-torrential-rain-causing-flooding-along-san-jacinto-river">affecting</a> thousands of residents. Our sincere best wishes are with everyone affected!</p>
<p>As we look to risk assessment, it’s important to determine how extreme this rainfall really was. <a href="../../people/grad-students/yuchen-lu.html">Yuchen Lu</a>, a third-year PhD student, compared the rainfall at different durations to Atlas 14 estimates of rainfall probability, finding that this was a 10 to 25-year event depending on how it’s analyzed. This underscores the importance of vulnerability reduction and flood preparedness.</p>
<p>You can find Yuchen’s more detailed analysis <a href="https://dossgollin-lab.github.io/SanJac2024_IDF/">here</a> or the source code <a href="https://github.com/dossgollin-lab/SanJac2024_IDF">on GitHub</a>.</p>
<p>As we look to managing future flood risks, further improvements to risk assessment are needed. Atlas 14 estimates are useful but do not account for the increasing likelihood of extreme weather. More fundamentally, probability distributions of annual maximum rainfall at a single point are completely silent on the spatial or temporal structure of rainfall, which can matter for flood impacts. We are working hard to address both of these limitations in our research – stay tuned for more updates!</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>News</category>
  <guid>https://dossgollin-lab.github.io/posts/2024/2024-05-14-san-jac-idf.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 14 May 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
